[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
let's talk about conservation of charge
a little
bit the most naive
version is that the amount of charge in
the world whatever the world means
doesn't change it just stays the
same that's the most naive version of it
now if that were all it were to it then
um it really wouldn't say very much if a
charge disappeared over here and
reappeared on Alpha centuri at exactly
the same instant of time exactly of
course we have to worry about relativity
and the fact that same instant of time
may be a little bit confusing but let's
let's uh let's get a little pre-
relativistic if a charge disappeared
over here and reappeared on Alpha centuy
instantaneously we would say charge is
conserved by that definition that total
charge doesn't change but uh we aren't
on Alpha centu it's uh too far away for
us to know what's happening there and so
in that sense if that's all there was to
charge conservation it wouldn't tell us
anything
it wouldn't tell us anything at all okay
if we could get to Alpha centuri and
check the charges there we could go to
Beta centuri or Gamma centu or or the
next galaxy over or whatever and we
would have exactly the same problem that
within a laboratory within our
laboratory charge conservation wouldn't
mean anything we'd have no way of
checking it now what is the way that we
check it can charge disappear from the
laboratory yes charge can disappear from
the laboratory it can reappear outside
the laboratory but in order to do so it
has to pass through the walls of the
laboratory and so some detector set up
at the walls of the laboratory to
monitor the flow of charge would would
uh
would what do detectors do they would
ring bells or uh or detect that's what
detectors do they detect they would
detect ring bells and we would know the
charge passed from the inside to the
outside that idea that conservation
means more than just the algebraic sum
of the charges in the world doesn't
change but it means that there's a
concept that when charge does disappear
from a place it identifiably moves
through the walls of a system through
the boundaries of the system that gets
Quantified in the idea of local charge
qu local charge
conservation or the idea of a current as
well as a charge a current is a flow of
charge so another way to say it is if
charge disappears from this room it's
because a current flowed through somehow
the boundaries of the room that's the
only way it can happen and a current
flowing through the boundaries of the
room is detectable at the walls of the
room so let's see if we can quantify
that not just quantify for um formalize
it turn it into a mathematical statement
of some sort and then check with our
little theory that we made up about
charge uh that well we'll go back to it
whether it satisfies that
Criterion all right first of all there's
the concept of CH yes is this is this
particularly different than a similar
statement about Mass no it is not
particularly different than statements
about mass now the difference is that um
I'll tell you what the difference is
mass by itself in a relativistic theory
doesn't really is not a conserved
quantity energy is the corresponding
conserved quantity all right energy and
it comes along with another conserved
quantity well three other conserved
quantities which are called momentum and
they form a complex but each one of them
is separately conserved and each one of
them has a
flow now in fact the momentum is the
flow of
energy but what's the flow of momentum
and that's something else called stress
now whether we'll get to the stress uh
uh it's called stress not the kind of
stress that you feel when you um when
you know you've lied to your wife but
then she's going to catch you but uh the
kind of stress that a material object
experiences when it when a force is
imposed on
it that I say something
about having lied and no no I didn't
mean that
um what this is 2000 you can't see this
is two 2008 2008 you can't do that
1960s I stopped doing it in the 1960s
that's
right but I stopped doing almost
everything in everything interesting in
the yeah so where were we we were
talking about charge flow and the first
concept is charge density now density is
not the motion of charge it's just a
local version of the idea of how much
charge is there local means it's
identified with a small region of space
there's the idea of charge density
charge density is just locally at some
at some particular location the charge
per unit volume that's present now to
Define it precisely we do a little bit
of calculus and a little bit of limiting
uh Notions we take a little box around
surrounding a point we take the total
charge in that box let's say this the
box is of size Epsilon it has a volume
Epsilon cubed we take the charge inside
that box let's call let's what's a good
name for charge q q is the standard uh
terminology for electric charge Q Inside
the Box this is not Q of the world this
is Q of the Box we divide it by the
volume of the
box and then we take the limit in which
both in which Epsilon goes to zero and
of course also Q goes to zero we take
the limit of Q over Epsilon as the Box
gets smaller and smaller and that's
called
row row for density I don't know why
it's called row and not D or Delta or
something else but it's Row for density
and it depends on position of course it
also depends on time the density of
charge change with time so whatever row
is it depends on position and
time okay what do we do with row well if
we know row we can say how much charge
is in any region of space in any region
of space let's take an arbitrary region
of space now with any shape whatever
then the amount of charge in there let's
also call it q but it doesn't stand for
the charge in a box now it stands for a
charge in a general region is then equal
to the integral
over that
region let's call it d3x meaning DX Dy
DZ over that region over the interior of
that region of
row and strictly speaking we could take
this to be the definition of charge
density it's the thing that you sum up
or integrate over a region of space to
find out how much charge is in there the
total charge in the universe you
integrate over everything in the world
and you know all of volume and that
gives you the total charge in the
universe but usually that's a fairly
useless concept the total charge in the
universe better integrate over the
region of the laboratory and that will
tell you how much charge is in your
laboratory
now next concept the flow of charge the
flow of charge is defined by a thing
called the current you used to think of
thinking about currents flowing through
wires uh we don't have to be thinking
about currents flowing through wires
we're thinking about charges flowing
through space clouds of charge flowing
through space and to quantify the idea
of a
current we take a little
area now this is an area in space a
little
square and we stand there and watch that
square and watch the charge passing
through that little square it's a little
window think of it as a
window small window
and charges go from one side of the
window through the window out to the
other side of the
window and we can ask how much charge
goes through the window per unit time we
can wait one second and see how much
charge goes through the window count
take that charge and divide it by the 1
second but we can also do calculus and
we can go to the limit of a very small
time interval I think that's the last
time I will say that that we'll take
limits we just imagine you know that we
you know how to take limits uh we study
the amount of charge that goes through
the window per unit
time okay now that's not yet the current
the amount of charge that will go
through that
window will not only be proportional to
the time element the little time that
that you allow but it'll also be
proportional to something else what is
it the area the area of the window the
bigger the area of the window the more
charge will go through
so if we take the charge that goes
through the window again let's call it
q and divide it by the area of the
window let's call it a and the little
time
interval what shall we call it delta T
the little time interval and then take
the limit as the window gets small and
as the time interval gets
small then we call that object the local
current at that point the point at the
center of the window there but it's a
particular it's a particular component
of the current the current is not a
scaler uh under rotations with respect
to rotations of space not with respect
to space time but with respect to
rotations of space the charge is a Scala
the amount of charge in a little region
doesn't matter which orientation you
draw
but the flow of charge is more like wind
velocity it has a direct associated with
it so for example if the charge happened
to be flowing along the x-axis here and
we took our window to be in the YZ plane
to be in the window uh along the
Blackboard here no charge would go
through that window it's like um a wind
blowing uh here's a
window and the wind is blowing in this
direction no wind goes through the
window but if it's turn the window so
that it's facing into the wind then wind
goes to the
window uh charge current current is a
vector a three-dimensional Vector a
vector in the sense of three-dimensional
space and if we Orient our
window so that the perpendicular to it
let's draw the perpendicular to it draw
a perpendicular let's say the
perpendicular then is along the x
axis right then the amount of charge
going through we call this an X window
an X oriented
window an x-oriented
window then and remember the x-axis is
perpendicular to the window an X
oriented window and we take the charge
through the x-oriented window per unit
area per unit time that becomes the X
component of the charge current
so that's called J it's called J again J
for current I don't know why J is used
is that usually called current density
it sometimes called current density
yeah yeah sometimes called yeah yeah
yeah um right okay so in elementary
physics the current is the current
Through the Wire in advanced physics it
becomes the current density and in super
Advanced physics we forget the word
density and we just call it the current
again right yeah right
uh right so in fact we will even come to
a terminology where we will call the
compli the complex of J together with
row we'll just call that the current
eventually but uh for the moment yeah
this is we would just call this the X
component of current and once you hear
component once you hear that it's a
component you know it's a vector and uh
that's a clue that it's the current
density it's a current density JX
incidentally the uh the symbol for the
current through a wire is I not J okay
so J is the current
density and again it's a thing that you
integrate you integrate it over time and
over the little area of the window to
find out how much total charge flows
through in a given
time J I call it small J but the I would
not be it
depends it depends sometimes in some
books it's capital I in some books it's
small I I've seen both
uh okay so that's JX and of course
there's JY and JZ what is JY and JZ you
take your window oriented along the Y
AIS and you ask notice incidentally that
there's a sense of orientation to this
window we're talking about the charge
that flows from the left to the right in
other words the charge that flows along
the positive x-axis from the negative to
the positive x-axis in the same way we
can Define JY and
JZ
JY would correspond to a window oriented
along the y- AIS and we would be talking
about the amount of charge per unit time
that flows from the negative y to the
positive y regions
and and likewise
JZ all right now what I
maintain is that any time current
disappears out of the room there will be
on the boundary of the room what do I
say that when current disappears charge
disappears if charge disappears out of
the room there will be a current on the
boundary okay and the current on the
boundary will
exactly um comp compensate the amount of
charge that flows through the boundaries
will exactly compensate for the amount
that the charge changes within the room
let's see if we can quantify that and
make an equation out of it let's take a
little
box uh it has six faces it's a little
Cube it has six faces and let's take
this to be the xaxis over
here now let's take a small amount of
time delta T and ask how much charge
let's I think we should probably uh give
this a size Epsilon Epsilon Epsilon in
every
direction how much charge flows into the
box through face number one over here
here's face number one how much charge
flows into the
box in a small interval of time delta T
flows into the box through face number
one
okay and the answer is going to be
JX at this point let's call this point
number one over
here it's also face number
one JX at the center of face number one
times the area Epsilon squar times the
amount of time delta
T all right that's how much charge go
into the box per unit time per unit area
from the left now let's through through
the X uh through the xace now there's
another xace over
here charge may be flowing out through
there so how much charge flows out
through
here
it's it's exactly the same expression
let's call this face number
two and let's call A point also Point
number two what will it be notice that
if J is positive if J is positive that
means charge is flowing into the box
it's flowing this way if J is positive
over here it means charge is Flowing out
of the box so we should
subtract JX at 0 2 I hear I hear the
right answer times the same times the
same
factor same area same time interval so
so the answer is let's write the answer
JX at 1 minus JX at
2 that's the change in charge inside the
box but wait a minute that's not all of
it that's only the stuff that flew in
through the x windows what about the Y
Windows well same kind of thing why
window down here can admit charge if the
current is positive if the if the Y
component of the current is positive
charge will flow into the box from the
bottom and it will flow out of the box
from the top and so there's another
term let's
call let's see let's call the bottom
face here
three and the top face four IV four and
also the centers will call 3 and
4 okay the area of the um bottom and top
faces are the same the unit of time is
the same and so what are we going to get
we're going to get
JY
of
3 minus
JY of
four that's the charge flowing in from
three and out from
four and then there's a last one the one
flowing in well I'm not sure which way
the z-axis goes the z-axis comes out of
of the
Blackboard yeah well I think so all
right so we we add this this is the
stuff that flows in the X Direction This
Is The Stuff that flows in the y
direction and finally the last term is
let's put it over here
plus oh
yeah the delta T * Epsilon multiplies
everything the last term you can guess
it's going to be
j
z now we have to name the uh well it's a
JZ it's again the difference of JC let's
call it at 5 minus JZ at
6 what is that that's the change in
charge that's the amount of charge that
flowed into the
box now imagine the box is small we're
going to imagine the box is small
Epsilon is going to be small in a
minute what is that equal to well as I
said that's equal to the increase in
charge that's equal to the increase in
charge so that must in fact if we divide
it by delta
T it's the time rate of change of charge
in the Box the time rate of change in
the box of charge in the box so that's d
by
DT of the charge in the Box
Q equal
to time rate of change of the charge
Inside the Box the stuff that flew in
minus the stuff that flew out gives us
the rate of change of the charge in the
Box okay now this J of one minus J of
two
the distance between one and two is
going to be shrunk to zero we're going
to take this little box and make it
smaller and
smaller the difference between J at 01
and J at Point 2 is just going to turn
into some kind of
derivative just the derivative of J
between two neighboring points the
difference between a quantity at two
neighboring
points what is it let's write an
equation over here J of 1 - JX of
2 that's
equal to the derivative of
JX with respect to
X not quite there's a minus sign here
it's j of one one is slightly to the
left of two J of 1 minus J of two would
be the derivative of J with respect to X
but of course we'd want to divide that
by Epsilon to make a real derivative out
of it
okay yeah we're going to get Epsilon Cub
that's right
so right that's right so this really can
be
reinterpreted as let's just reinterpret
it over here Epsilon
squared now I'm going to want to put an
Epsilon downstairs so let's put an
Epsilon downstairs and just as Michael
said
if we put an Epsilon downstairs we've
got to compensate by an Epsilon
upstairs well that's kind of neat this
is the volume Epsilon cubed that's
that's going to play a nice role keep in
mind the volume over here and then some
derivatives of J what's it going to be
it's going to be Epsilon
cubed and three terms the derivative of
JX with respect to
X plus the derivative of JY with respect
to to Y plus the derivative of JZ with
respect to Z and I think I have an
overall minus
sign
uh what is that that's the time rate of
change DQ by
DT now let's divide by Epsilon cubed if
we divide this by Epsilon
cubed let's divide it by Epsilon cubed Q
over Epsilon
cubed Q is the charge in the
Box Epsilon is the Vol Epsilon cubed is
the volume of the Box what is Q over
Epsilon Q over Epsilon
cubed the charge density right
so and this this derivative of course
means standing at the same point we stay
in the same box we're not moving around
as we're doing this so that really means
means the partial derivative of the
density with respect to time partial
derivative because we're keeping the
positions fixed so the right hand side
just becomes the partial derivative with
respect to time of the charge
density
uh yeah minus sign is
correct if I transfer what's in the
bracket over to the right hand side
or put everything on the same side then
I get an
equation it's called the continuity
equation and what it says is the time
rate of change of
density
plus the Divergence of the current for
those who know what a Divergence is this
is the Divergence of the current I'll
write it out
explicitly
DX
JX let's d by DX I said I would write it
explicitly and I
will plus Dy
JY
no sometimes written Just
J just a second plus
DZ j z = z say it again is sometimes
that's just written Just J D J the
Divergence of J without without any
without any subs del. J right we think
of this is
right right so we have we could write
this as we could also write this row dot
if I wanted to save myself some symbols
plus del. J is equal to
zero what does that Express that
expresses the fact that the only way
that the charge can change in there is
by charge flowing into or out of the
system it doesn't change by itself in
other words if there's no current
through the walls the charge doesn't
change in here it relates the change in
charge to the flow through the boundary
that's the Deep concept of
conservation deep and useful concept of
conservation that the time oh and we can
uh let's see um why don't I put
everything on the same side if I brought
all of this to the right hand side it
would all be pluses right so I think we
can do that efficiently by just putting
d r by DT over
here and adding plus over here getting
rid of brackets and setting the right
hand side equal to
zero now this has an interesting look to
it let me write this in a
rather minus sign no no minus sign in
this
equation the minus sign um got eaten
up by transposing
uh well when I transposed the D Ro DT to
the to the left hand side it picked up a
minus and then I multiplied the whole
equation by
minus
okay let's make up a new notation
what's that J T yeah right well except
that we're going to change it a little
bit we're going to call
row
J Super T not subt or remember that
sometimes we think of TX Y and Z as x0
X1 X2 and
X3 let's use that
notation and we combine these all
together and call them X mu now we're
talking relativity and we're talking
about uh four vectors and all that kind
of stuff all right so let's call row
let's call it J knot it looks like it's
got something to do with time it
does let's call JX the thing that I've
called
JX let's now think of it as an object
with an upper index so I'm sorry I
defined this way I should have defined
it with an upper
index I would not have had to switch in
the middle of this argument let's just
Define it everywhere as the same
quantity with the
indices now it's just pure notation
there's nothing no content to it I've
just changed my notation slightly same
thing for
Z same thing for
Z but we already got learned through
that before where what we used to think
of as lower indices turn out to be the
things that we want to be upper indices
with a sign
change uh we where we change the sign of
the time component yeah yeah but now now
it's just definition now it's just
definition JX JY and JZ with the upper
index are exactly the things which I
previously should have defined in the
first place as having upper indices I
didn't uh didn't realize that while I
Was preparing my notes but I should have
all right
so we take these four objects row JX JY
and JZ and we can now write this whole
equation in the compact
form derivative sub mu the derivative
with respect to X
mu of J super
mu equals
z all right the first term is derivative
with respect to X not that means
derivative with respect to time of J not
that's this
one and then when mu is one we have the
derivative of the X component of J with
respect to X and so
forth this of course is summed over mu
but I'm using the Einstein summation
convention now and it becomes quite
clear that this that J mu is a four
Vector J mu is a four Vector I won't
prove that but it does transform as a
four vector and it's pretty darn clear
from this equation that this equation
wouldn't make sense in every frame of
reference the derivation of the the
derivation of the argument did not
depend on what frame of reference I was
in it was a very general derivation it
must be true in every frame of reference
and the only way that an equation like
this can be true in every frame of
reference is that if J transforms the
four vector and it does so we have a new
version of conservation
in terms of a lorence invariant
continuity equation this is called the
continuity
equation and it's the
uh
powerful
principle that basically tells us that
charge cannot disappear in one place and
reappear in another without flowing
through the boundaries of the region
so I could also write
this D mu j mual
0 incidentally it would not change if I
put this index upstairs and that index
downstairs you can juggle the indices up
and down as long as you keep them
balanced and I won't go through that but
there will be times when equations might
come out with one a little differently
with this index upstairs that index
downstairs it's the same equation
okay
good now let's go back to the derivation
from n's
theorem of the charge density for a
simple field theory that had a certain
symmetry I'll just review it for you
quickly it provided for us a concept of
a conserved quantity which I called
charge and in fact that charge was
written as an integral over a space so
it's clear that the thing that we
defined must be the charge density the
question is does that same theorem
provide us or does something provide us
with a notion of J not uh of this J of
the space components of the other
components of the current and so let's
go back and uh
review all I wrote down a particular
field Theory which involved a field with
complex valued uh Field Complex value
Field Complex value field of course just
means two real
Fields so I wrote f is equal to 51 plus
I
2 51 F star is equal to 51 minus iy
2 and you can just think if you like you
you needn't use this complex notation
the complex notation is is notationally
neat but you can just think in terms of
F1 and 52 you can imagine an internal
space this is not real space this is an
imaginary space whose axes are 51 and 5
2 and then the value of a field at any
point of space or any point of space
time for that matter is a DOT whoops
that's not a very good
dot there's a
DOT on on the plane F1 5 2 thought of as
the complex plane or just the ordinary
real plane with two axes that's the
field if this is five then five star is
down
here all right the Symmetry that we're
going to imagine is a symmetry under
rotating this plane in other words let's
ask the question supposing the lran did
not vary if we rotated the field in this
plane we have to do it everywhere is in
space
simultaneously so everywhere is in space
simultane and in time we rotate the axes
of uh of f an equivalent thing to
do is to multiply the complex fi by a
phase Factor one way of describing the
rotations of the plane is just to say
that f is replaced by f * e to the I
Epsilon where Epsilon could be any real
number in particular we could take a
small real number and this would just be
a small rotation of the of the axes so
this is one way to
describe uh such a rotation of axes
another way to describe it in particular
for a small for Epsilon small in other
words just a small angular rotation of
the axis is just to say what happens to
F1 and 5 2 I'll tell let's write the
Delta F1 the change in F1 if you just
change axes by a little bit small
rotation angle
Epsilon what happens to to F1 it gets
changed by amount Delta F1 which is
proportional I'll just write equal to 5
2 * Epsilon time the small angle and
what about Delta 5
2 it's of course proportional to Epsilon
but uh
just
51 minus
51 now how do you look at a l grangian
and decide whether it's invariant under
this
operation well in particular if it's
written in complex form if it's written
in complex form it's really easy if it
contains things like f star five in
it that's invariant if I star five
doesn't change if you multiply five by a
little phase the same time F star goes
to F star * e to the minus I Epsilon and
so if you multiply five by F star the
epsilons will just cancel out five F
star which is also incidentally the same
as 5 1^ 2 plus 5 2^
2 five star five is invariant so if the
L grangian for example contained F star
five it could contain F star 5^ squared
in fact it can contain any function of F
star five this in itself is invariant
and so that would uh that would ensure
or this term in lran would be invariant
what if it contained things like d
muf time D muf
star still invariant
because if fi changes by a phase the
derivative of fi changes by exactly the
same phase
what about a thing like 5
squ is that
invariant no because 5^ squar what will
happen to 5^ squar 5^
squared
will get e to 2 I Epsilon when you
multiply five by e to the I Epsilon five
star five the e to the I epsilons will
cancel i^ squar they will not cancel so
there are certainly things which are not
invariant
uh if you had something like 5 1^ 2 + 3
f 2^ 2 would that be
invariant no but how about 5 1^2 plus 5
2^ 2 yes all right
so it's relatively easy to look at a
lran and to see whether it's invariant
under this operation if written in terms
of complex notations then it should
involve products of fields time complex
conjugates if it's written in terms of
the real components it should involve
sums of squares of things with index one
and things with index two let's suppose
that's the case let's suppose that alian
is invariant all right then there's a
symmetry if there's a symmetry there's a
conservation law let's remember the form
of such conservation laws
there's a conserved quantity which is
often called capital Q sometimes it's
even called small q and the reason it's
called capital Q or small q is because
it's going to wind up being some sort of
charge so it's related to the thing
we've already called charge but let's
just call it Q sometimes called the
nther
charge right what you do is you sum over
the whole
system the change this Q is not the core
coordinates it's capital Q it's a charge
you take the
change in the I
coordinate and you multiply
it by the I momentum let's call it P P
subi this is the canonical momentum
conjugate to Q
subi typically Delta Q subi will have an
Epsilon in it right
just drop the Epsilon well you can leave
the Epsilon there and then throw it away
at the end we don't need to worry it's
just just a numerical multiple a small
numerical multiple of a quantity we
could divide it we could divide out the
Epsilon the Epsilon is of no importance
whatever this is the quantity which is
conserved I think the last time I called
these Delta Q's I think I called them F
I think I wrote that Delta
Q is equal to Epsilon * F well that's a
redundant notation just call it Delta q
and forget the Epsilon at the end of the
story that's the conserved quantity the
sum over all the variables of the
canonical momentum multiplied by the
small shift in the quanti in the
coordinate when you do the Symmetry
operation so now we can write that down
very quickly Q for our case now is the
integral over
space that replaces
sum what about
Pabi that's the iCal momentum conjugate
to
fi there's two of them F1 and 5 2 so we
can write Pi
1 that's the canonical momentum
conjugate to uh to the first
field F1 times Delta F1 what is Delta F1
it's 5
2 plus pi 2 * Delta 51
but that's minus pi1 did I say something
wrong I think I did minus Pi 2 times the
change here which is minus
51 that's what Emy Nera tells us would
be the conserved quantity conserved
because of the
Symmetry now let's go back to the
original lran that we had imagined the
original agian that we imagined involved
time derivatives and space derivatives
but in particular it involved time
derivatives and the time derivatives
were in the
form DF by
DT squared
12 can forget everything else for the
moment this was the kinetic term in the
Lan remember what the canonical momentum
is the canonical momentum is the
derivative of the lran with respect to
the
velocity well that's just the derivative
of the lran with respect to D DT and
that's just D DT Pi 1 is D1 by
DT
pi2 is D2 by
DT and so now we have an expression for
the charge here it
is equals integral over
space times pi 1 which is let's just
call it 51 dot * 5 2 minus 52 dot *
51 this quantity must be conserved we've
proved it we've proved it a dozen times
already over we proved it by proving a
more General theorem here's the more
General theorem that this is conserved
this is the conserved quantity and it's
an integral over
space now to get a perspective on what
this
is on the meaning of it it's helpful to
go back to the analogy with a string I
think we talked about this but let's do
it
again uh a string or a rope a jump rope
something like that stretched between
two points free to move around our first
version of the of the string was that it
was free to move in the vertical
plane now I want to have it be free also
to move in the horizontal plane not move
along the direction of the
string or transverse to the direction of
string in both directions let's call One
Direction by one and the other direction
52 think of them in in a model we're
making up a model of a Theory now I
don't want you to think of a real jump
rope I mean for the moment think of a
real jump rope but ultimately we'll be
thinking about mathematical Fields
describing relativistic uh field Theory
and so forth but for our purposes right
now you can actually think of 51 and 52
as the X and Y coordinates of a point on
this now what is this what is 51
dot F1 dot is
a one component of the
Velocity so this is like the one
component of the Velocity times the
other component of position minus vice
versa that should be familiar to many of
you as the angular
momentum all right so if
we if we really think about the
mechanical analogy then the five dots
would be velocities and of course
velocities are proportional to momenta
ordinary momenta now just ordinary
momenta and uh this would be like the X
component of momentum * Yus the Y
component of momentum time
x that would be called the angular
momentum the angular
momentum about an axis along the string
so think of the jump rope being twirled
around it has some angular
momentum uh you don't really have to
have anybody there twirling you can just
have it anchored to some point and you
give it a a whirl and it continues to
whirl and it doesn't stop unless it's
friction of course friction will stop it
but in the absence of
friction uh it will just continue to
whirl around you can whirl it around
with a node so that half of it is over
here the other half is over here and
both of them are whirling around like
this that would be positive angular
momentum going in the other way would be
negative angular momentum oh I could do
that I didn't know if I could do that
I can't do this
though
uh right so that's angular momentum
about this
axis that's the analog that's the
analogy for charge that's the analogy
the mechanical analogy of in the jump
rope case for charge but with or without
the analogy this is the expression now
this can be written another way another
compact way I'll write it in another
compact way you can write it in terms of
the complex
components let me write it in terms of
components it's also the integral over
space
DX
uh of I think this's an
i and then there is
a no F1 and 5 2 but F
star do
fi minus
F star fi dot if you work this out in
terms of the components F1 and 5 2 you
get exactly the same thing notice that
the two terms are complex conjugates of
each
other and when you subtract what do you
get when you subtract two complex
conjugates pure imaginary but if you
multiply it by I it becomes pure
real uh so you can also write this if
you like I think this a factor of two
there's a factor of two if I remember no
which is not terribly important if thing
is conserved then twice it is also
conserved but technically I think
there's a factor of two there we can
also write this in another form as just
the imaginary
part the imaginary part of the integral
of f star.
f if you take two things and you
subtract a thing from its uh complex
conjugate you that leaves over only the
imaginary part so it's the imaginary
part of five star five if you work out
not five star five five star dot times
five that's a way to write it it's a
neat efficient way to write
it and then we can just concentrate on
f. f. starfi and remember at the end
that we should take its imaginary part
and that uh that defines the charge for
us all right it's just a notational
device that allows us to avoid writing
so many uh indices and things and just
write that the charge density is
imaginary part of the time derivative of
five star * 5 what about the term with f
dot time F
star did I forget to write
it no when you take the imaginary part
of something you subtract ra the thing
from its complex
conjugate so they're both
there okay that's
uh a useful set
of
notations now
our um goal is well first of all it's
quite clear that this imaginary part of
f star. f is the charge density it's the
thing that we integrate over space to
get the charge if this is indeed some
sort of charge if indeed I've accurately
identified what this object is and it's
some sort of charge then this thing in
here is the charge density or this thing
this thing in here is the charge
density sign does that matter well it
doesn't really because uh you can either
Define the charge or negative the
charge uh somewhere is along the line
there was a convention which I've
forgotten right now but it's strictly a
Convention of which you call positive
and which you call negative and it
really doesn't matter CU I'm I'm
thinking that there's a minus sign from
the left hand side to the imaginary
notation uh That Could That Could well
be
so um
let's could well be I'm not going to try
to track it now it'll waste time but
it's uh one sign or the other and the
important point the important fact is
that it's not important
it's important to be consistent but it's
not important uh when you're making your
definition of what you want to call
charge to fix one sign or the other you
fix a sign and then you stick with it so
let's use this uh let's use this
notation with the minus sign here
the I I hate carrying around the minus
sign oh I know what I can do I can get
rid of the minus
sign Yeah by putting the star on the
other side yeah good
okay so that's
uh that's and this object then the
imaginary part of this object what is it
it's the charge
density okay so let me write down then
we have the following ideas we have an
idea of what the charge density is and
we have the idea of a four Vector of
charge
current the integrand you're saying is
the charge density that's correct the
charge density is a thing that you
integrate to find the
charge all right so let's write it down
then row be angular momentum density it
would be an angular momentum per unit
length along the string
yeah right angular momentum per unit
exactly uh I think I probably mentioned
last time that uh
that this of course has a um important
there an important concept here that is
not important now but will become quite
important when we do some quantum
mechanics with these
ideas and identifying the charge as
being s similar to an angular momentum
mathematically it has the properties of
an angular momentum and you will of
course remember that in quantum
mechanics angular momentum is quantized
it comes in integer multiples of Harr
positive or
negative uh that suggests that when we
apply quantum mechanics to Fields like
this that the charge will be quantized
and indeed it is uh for the same
mathematical
reasons you don't need to know what
those mathematical reasons are you
simply need to know that there's a
mathematical similarity or more than a
similarity an
isomorphism between the theory of charge
in field Theory and the theory of
angular momentum to know that uh that if
one is quantized the other will be
quantized and that's the origin of the
fact that charge comes in multiples of
something
um and I won't get into quarks which
carry a third of a unit of charge here
this is not the place for right now
that's
a a sophisticated
subtlety okay so let's see so where were
we
um yeah currents currents all right so
let's write
row row is the imaginary part of
something uh and what is that
something time derivative of
f time F
star look at it for a minute and then
try to
guess what the other components of the
four Vector are
now notice that this index here is a
lower index a derivative defines a first
of all this object the derivative with
respect to T defines is it covariant or
contravariant I can't remember coar the
covariant components of a four Vector f
is assumed to be a scal of field so this
is a covariant component of a four
vector and of course multiplying it by a
scaler it is still the covariant
component of a four Vector it's pretty
obvious what the other components of the
covariant components of the four Vector
are they are just imaginary
part of five star let's called all four
components D byd mu of
five that's the completion of the four
Vector for
example J
X is equal to the imaginary part of f
star DX
F and so forth what about the upper
components what about the contravariant
components what is J Super
X same thing but what about J Super
T Min a minus
sign okay we could take all of that into
account by simply inventing a notation
which keeps track of the signs by
putting the indices upstairs now all
this means a derivative with a
superscript there just means change the
sign for the time component so that's
just a uh a neat little uh trick that
you can do to keep track of signs it
doesn't change anything and then we're
writing the
uh the
contravariant
components covariant contravariant they
only differ by a sign uh in the time
component want to write the star on the
bottom say it again
just you want to lower the star right
yeah don't lower
stars but that actually does have a
meaning we don't want to we don't want
to fool with
it
uh all right now Next
Step can we directly prove that this
four-dimensional Vector satisfies the
continuity
equation all right we would like to show
that this object does really satisfy the
continuity equation that's where we came
in with the continuity
equation uh and I think we'll take a
little break but at the end after the
break we will derive the continuity
equations from the field equations you
can't get them from nowhere you got to
get them from somewhere what do we have
we know some things about how fi moves
in space and time how it varies in space
and time and if we're lucky it will be
enough to prove for us that the
continuity equation is satisfied for J
so that'll be the next step prove the
continuity
equation
uh notice we really have not proved the
continuity equation what we proved using
n's theorem is the conservation law all
that really tells us is that the total
charge in the universe doesn't change
with time we have not really proved the
continuity equation so that's a separate
thing to prove but uh it is true so
we'll come back to it in about s
minutes okay our goal is to check the
continuity equation our goal I think is
to wait for the uh remainder of the
class to come in
first called isotopic spin isotopic spin
it does but uh I think uh not for the
electron
um
yeah there the answer is yes it has
something to do with it but
uh
but it is not the same
thing something different we'll get to
it I think we'll I think we'll be able
to talk about isotopic spin
unfortunately we have to talk about
Spinners which we uh which is a subtlety
but we'll try we'll try our
best
um
yeah so we have we have a
guess for what the four-dimensional four
Vector of current flow is and the only
thing to check there's only one thing to
check and that's the check that it is
conserved meaning to say that it
satisfies continuity equation uh these
days when a physicist says something is
conserved he literally means that the
current that the number one that there
is a notion of current and charge
density or density of whatever the
quantity is number one and that it
satisfies the continuity equation
continuity equation is always Central to
what a physicist means by saying
something is
conserved okay so we ought to then check
the continuity
equation now the continuity equation has
to do with the way the components of J
vary in space and time we're going to
differentiate them after all and that in
turn has to do with the way fi varies in
space and time what is it which controls
the way that it varies with space and
time the field equations so in order to
write some field equations let's
begin with a simple L grangian we're not
going to do this for every possible L
grangian although we should and it would
be true for every lran of the right form
with the right symmetry but let's take a
particular lrange and our favorite um
that we've used over and over again
lrange density equal
to uh 5 do let's say 5 do^ 2 over 2
minus the space derivatives of
f squar same thing for Y and
Z over
two and uh then let's add what I have
been calling in a mass term just for fun
this is f^ squ I'm sorry I I withdraw
this it's f star.
f.
not2
star DX F
star now remember you can write this in
terms of usual components 51 and F two
and it's just this two lran one for each
component of the field and then I want
to add something just for fun or just
for a little bit more completeness let's
see do I want minus or plus
minus minus mu^ 2 where mu is just a
real number times five star
five I know in previous lectures I might
have just called this mu I don't
remember
X X Y and Z all of
them it's not it's just an X and A Y and
a z but we can write the whole thing we
can write the whole thing in the form d
mufi uh D mu V
Star that's all it
is will you have L equals five star
five is that a mu on I here no no just
what's that it's five star dot five star
Dot and then what's five dot five dot oh
okay you got two stars in the middle
ter oh yeah oh two stars in the middle
term sorry
good one star in the middle term all
right I only write it in this form to
just display the obvious symmetry that
it contains things times their complex
conjugates and so it has this symmetry
that uh that we've been talking about
all right the important point the
important thing is the field equations
which follow from this so oh there
should be a two over
here ah the twos are not important no no
no two there no two okay the important
thing is the field equation which
follows from this the field equation is
just we've written it before without the
MU squ term just let's write it out
explicitly the derivative with respect
to time of f minus the second derivative
with respect to X Y and Z I'm just going
to include x but we also have a term for
y and
z y and then from here let's see I think
there's either a plus or a minus
um
uh plus I
think plus mu
^2 5 = 0
this without the MU squ it would just be
the usual wave equation that we've
written down many
times we make it into three-dimensional
wave equation by putting a y and a z
term adding them in and then this mu squ
term is just another term uh that uh
that's uh I'm including for completeness
or semi completeness just to have it
there we'll use it later we'll study it
later at play some important role in the
mass of a particle but for the moment
it's just a uh an extra term I threw in
to be a little more
complete okay um here's our field
equation now I can write it in a very
compact
form it
is D super mu d sub mu
V either plus or minus let me get this
right
[Music]
um I think minus mu ^2
f equals
z so this is a nice compact form for it
and it stands for the second derivative
with respect to time minus the second
derivative with respect to
space okay that's our field equation
what we want to derive from this field
equation is the continuity equation for
J so let's write the continuity equation
for J and see if it
follows the continuity equation for J is
D mu J mu equals z so let's just do
it this will this if it's true then it
means that this is what it would mean it
means the imaginary part of d
mu
on F
star D mu
5 equals
z that's what it would
mean
J here's J the imaginary part anyway we
differentiate it and set it equal to
zero well I'm not saying it's true I'm
saying is it
true not it is true but is it true
okay let's check it let's follow it
through a little bit it's the same thing
as now I can differentiate I can write
that this is the imaginary part and the
derivative here consists of two terms in
one term the D mu hits the F star in the
other term the D mu hits the derivative
all right so what does it got we have
two terms then we have D mu F star D
mufi that's when the derivative hits the
F star
then we have plus F
star D mu D
mu
F does this or does this not equal
zero that's our
question so let's look at it
first thing is this is real it consists
of things like the time derivative of
five star times the time derivative of f
things times their own complex
conjugates with various signs the signs
don't change don't turn something real
into imaginary so this is pure real and
its imaginary part is just
zero good that was fast we got rid of
that fast this piece here is clearly
related to the field equation where's
the field equation the field equation
has exactly that same thing in it D mu D
muf and it's equal to Mu ^ 2 5 by virtue
of the field equations this becomes
equal to the imaginary part of f
star now D mu d muf That's mu^ 2
f plus or
minus I don't know plus or minus
whichever but this is just five star
five mu is real Five Star five is real
yeah am I just confused or you're
using oh oh I'm sorry very good i' yes
I've used me for two different things
index and let's call it
m let's call it m it is connected with
the mass of a particle but it differs
from the mass of a particle described as
a Quantum of the field by a factor of H
bar that's why I didn't want to call it
m but never mind I don't you are right
we H bar is equal to
one m
s yes but of course since we're doing
classical physics that means H is equal
to
zero
so
yeah but F star five is also real pure
real and so this is also zero so the
whole damn thing is
zero the whole thing is zero but not uh
not as a as an identity but by virtue of
the field equations by virtue of setting
this thing equal to this thing that's
the field equations in other words for
any solution of the equations of
motion not for any old F that you can
write down but for any fi which
satisfies the equations of
motion this
derivative D muj
mu is equal to
zero again I'll repeat why this is real
its imaginary part of zero this is not
obviously real but the equations of
motion tell us that it's equal to F star
m^2 5 one F star comes from here the
other F comes from the equation of
motion so the continuity equation is
indeed
satisfied okay so that's uh that um that
in itself doesn't establish that this is
the electric charge of
anything what it is is the electric
charge of the Assembly of charged
particles that might be the Quant of the
five
field
uh but it doesn't prove that this
charge what it does is it makes this a
candidate it's a conserved quantity a
quantity which satisfies a continuity
equation and it makes it a possible
candidate for a mathematical description
of charge and uh we're not going to go
more deeply into that right now is that
enough to say Quantity something it's
yes yes if we knew a little more I would
make a more complete argument but for
the moment it just establishes it as a
candidate for for an interesting
quantity that's conserved that satisfies
a continuity equation and among such
quantities in physics are electric
charge uh now uh we'll we'll come back
to this you asked me about isotopic spin
I'll tell you very quickly isotopic spin
of course has to do with nuclear physics
and it's it's connected with all of this
but I'll just tell you very quickly we
imagined the theory here in which the
field had two components F1 and 52
and the Symmetry was an invariance with
respect to rotation in the
plane in a theory of isotopic spin which
is not a theory of electric charge well
it can be partly a theory but the theory
of isotopic spin is just basically a
theory with three with three
components in which there are three axes
to the fields which are rotationally
invariant in three dimensions internal
Dimensions not real Dimensions but
internal dimensions and and otherwise is
extremely similar to
this so the pattern would be the
same
uh what happens to angular momentum in
three-dimensional
World angular momentum if there's only
two axes is either plus or minus goes
this way or goes this way what about
angular momentum when you're in a
three-dimensional
World it becomes a vector which means
that's three comp
components right three distinct
components any one of which could be
positive or negative and the isotopic
spin is a thing which has three distinct
components uh and so in a certain sense
it describes three charges not just one
charge but let's not
uh all right I want to talk a little
more about energy and momentum in
relativity and its Connection in
particular with mass and its connection
with this guy over here
I don't think we'll get to the full
story tonight we'll continue it next
time but I want to get to the story I
want to go back to ordinary special
relativity let's forget field Theory and
let's talk about the motion of particles
in ordinary relativity
Theory and identify in ordinary
relativity Theory the energy and
momentum of a
particle oh I know how we can do this we
can do this by the method of
Lans however we
won't maybe next
time on further
reflection I think I
won't all right um there a concept of
momentum in non-relativistic physics
it's mass time velocity the concept of
momentum in relativistic physics is also
mass time velocity those of you who have
taken uh my class previously in
relativity and things would know that
it's not masstimes ordinary velocity but
it's mass time four
velocity the ordinary velocity is the
components of a three Vector mass times
mass times what am I saying ordinary
momentum is a component of a three
vector and that three Vector involves
the three Vector of velocity the three
ve Vector of velocity is the three
components of spatial position their
derivative with respect to time in other
words D xdt dydt and dzdt let's just
write d xdt as one of
them the four Vector of
velocity is a four
vector and it's the derivative not with
respect to ordinary time but with
respect to proper time let's call it TOA
it has four components including a Time
component so there's a notion of the
time component of velocity and the
velocity forms a four Vector now this is
obviously a four Vector to is proper
time it's invariant it's a scalar X is a
vector or DX is a vector and so this is
a four Vector but before we go on let me
remind you what D to
is D to is a thing whose
square is DT d^ 2 minus dx^
2 minus Dy s minus d y^ 2 I need a
notion for the square of three vectors I
need a notation for the square of three
vectors let's just call it d x Vector
squared like that stands for DX squ D y^
squ and DZ s that's the t s now there's
some speeds of light in there where did
the speeds of light go
I think I usually like to put them
here some people like to put it in front
of the DT squared but then DT doesn't
have the same units as DT and so proper
time and time don't have the same units
I want proper time and time to have the
same units I put the C Square down here
and then since C is one and one is zero
and uh
no let's just I'll tell you where the
C's go when when when it's important to
know where the C's go but for the moment
C is equal to 1 all right this is dt^
squ the to is of course Square < TK of
DT ^2 minus dx^ 2 but now let's divide
and
multiply by DT let's put a DT here and a
DT here now I've done nothing but now I
want to bring the denominator DT into
the square root
to do so I have to square
it okay DT ^2 over t^2 what is that dt^
2 over dt^ s that's
one one now what is dx^ s or DX Vector
squar divided by dt^
2 threedimensional square with a
three-dimensional
velocity minus V vector squ 1 - v^
2 since I'm squaring it I don't even
have to put the uh it just means by
definition the sums of the squares good
now where would the speed of light go in
this
formula under the V v^2 over
c^2 that means for ordinary velocities
let's put it in for the moment for
ordinary velocities small by comparison
with the speed of light DT and DT are
almost the same thing
they're almost the same thing to within
a very very small correction but for
velocity is up near the speed of light
it's pretty important let's write this
one other way the to ided by DT or
better yet DT / D
to is equal to 1 / the sare < TK of 1 -
V ^2 over c^2 and let's just we'll put
back the C when we need it for various
purposes don't you have a isn't a DTC on
the
outside no
no no put the C inside you have to put a
c outside no no no I I'm I'm I'm
not no no it's right it's right I just
to restore the units I realized that too
and T have exactly the same units so I
can't put a c out here that would change
the units of the le- hand side and the
right hand
side but
V by itself one has no units one is
dimensionless and so v^2 over c^2 has to
be
dimensionless so that means it's got the
it's the ratio of V to C it's
right okay yeah um
good now let's compute the various
components of the four velocity the
first component of the four velocity or
the zeroth component is DT by D to and
here it
is 1 over the < TK of 1 - v^2 1 - v^2
over c^2 but I'll leave that now what
about the X component the X component is
DX by D
to but let's write that as DX by
[Music]
DT time DT by D
to but what what is DT by D to it's 1
the < TK of 1 - V
^2 so that means let's let's write the
equation let's write the equation
properly DX by D
to is equal to DX by
DT time DT by D to which is the same 1/
< TK 1 - V
^2 but what is DX by
DT that's just the X component of the
velocity
VX all right let's put back the C
squares the only place this a c^ s is
over
here 1 - v^2 over c^2 is where the uh
C's
go also over
here these are now the components of a
four
Vector well these are the first two
components of a four Vector the other
components would involve a Y and a
VZ so here's our four
Vector DX mu by D to consists
of 1 over the < TK of 1 - V ^
2 and V over theun of 1 -
v^2 that's our four vector
one component over here and then three
more components over
here now let's move on to
momentum momentum in non-relativistic
physics is just mass times
velocity velocity means ordinarily DX by
DT it's not a very good quantity from
the point of view of relativistic
physics it doesn't have a distinct
transformation property it's D X by D to
that has the good transformation
property so it was Einstein's guess and
then he confirmed that guess by various
gunkan experiments that when you go from
Newton to special relativity you should
replace MV or MDX by
DT by MDX by
DT and that would wind up being the
momentum the X component of momentum of
a
particle well
just the usual three components of
momentum all right so what does that
mean now here are the here here is DX by
D to and what it says then is that this
is equal to the mass times the velocity
yeah here's the three components divided
by sare < TK of 1 minus V
^2 now there Einstein made the guess
based
on uh his rule that everything should
have distinct and and uh good
transformation properties on the Lorent
Transformations that the momentum of
ordinary non-relativistic physics would
get corrected by a factor ofun of 1
minus v^2 in the denominator the very
small correction when V is
small especially when V over C is small
a very small correction not worth uh
very much when the velocity of an object
is small it gets a little bit sick when
you get up near the speed of light when
V gets up near the speed of light you
gets a denominator which gets closer and
closer to zero so the momentum gets very
much bigger than just mass time
velocity uh but that's okay this was his
formula and it is the correct formula
now the question is what is the fourth
component the fourth component here was
something
new the fourth component would be M time
DT by DC
and that's just the
mass let's call it
P the time component of the momentum
whatever that means and that will wind
up being just the mass ided the square <
TK of 1 - V ^2 /
c^2 that's just multiplying the mass by
DT by DT
to so Einstein said what is this
thing and he realized very quickly that
it was just the kinetic energy of the
particle it was the kinetic energy and
that indeed just as with Newtonian
physics a free particle would have four
conservation laws three of momentum and
one of
energy okay now if uh it's not quite
it's not quite right the factors of C
aren't quite in the right place to
Define uh conventional units of energy
what do I have to do to get conventional
units of energy in
there
h two powers of C in the
numerator so let's let's if I call it P
not this is correct but if I want to
identify that with energy I have to
write that there's another factor of c^2
m c^ 2 / < TK of 1 - V ^2 over
c^2 all right so for particle at rest V
equal 0 its energy is
mc^2 uh and the fact it's a c squ here
that's a convention or it just makes it
consistent with non-relativistic uh
units but let's let's leave it there e
is equal to mc^2 over theun of 1 - v^2
over c^2 but basically what it is is the
uh is the time component of a four
Vector which is composed out of the mass
times the four velocity that's energy
and momentum
um so we work out that what this all
right let's let's work out a little
further let's calculate what this is
when V over C is very
small when V over C we use the binomial
theorem the thing that's in the
denominator is 1 - v^2 / c^2 to the -2
power
all time mc^
2 now anybody remember the binomial
theorem well enough to expand this
out 1 + 12 V2 over
c^2 plus higher
orders this is equal to 1 plus v ^2 over
2 c^
2 all time mc^ 2
that's the expansion of this remember
that V over C is very small v s over c^2
is very small and if you expand it in
powers of v^2 over c^2 the first
correction to ones starts with 1 then
v^2 over 2 c^2 and then things which are
truly incredibly small V to 4 over C to
the 4th those are really really small
much smaller than this now what does
this give us this gives us MC
squar that's good
old famous Einstein MC squar
plus the
mass times v^
2 over two and the C squar is cancel C
squ in the denominator and C squ in the
numerator okay so what do we get we get
MC s the rest energy of a particle plus
the ordinary kinetic energy of course
this was the first indication of
Einstein's uh idea of equals mc^
s uh for an object at rest for an object
at rest eal mc^2 and then the first
correction is MV ^2 / 2 and the higher
Corrections involve much notice that the
C's cancel out of here the next
Corrections would truly be small by a
diminishing
factors of 1 over
c^2 okay that I just wanted to make sure
that
we
understood not
theer it is the proper Mass it's the
it's the rest
Mass this m yeah yeah that's just look
physicists don't even use the term rest
Mass anymore that the term rest Mass
hasn't been used for
75 years only in uh in elementary
physics classes are the only place where
the and even there I don't think goal to
you right the mass of the particle is a
property of the particle which doesn't
care whether the particle is moving or
not
uh and it is the energy of the particle
when or the energy of an object when the
center of mass of that object is at rest
that's the definition of a mass take an
object it could be a pot of hot water it
could be
um whatever it happens to be put it at
rest which means make sure that its
total momentum is equal to zero whatever
its energy is is called its mass with
within a factor of c^ s okay so m means
rest Mass I will never ever talk about
rest mass or moving Mass we'll just talk
about mass and it means what used to be
called 10,000 years ago
uh used to be called the rest
Mass
uh
right anyway this is energy and momentum
now it's kind of interesting you get
into some very peculiar mess when you
try to think about particles whose mass
is zero looks like their energy is zero
but the problem is when a particle has
zero Mass it also moves with a speed of
light and so the denominator is also
zero you get into a nasty um Z over zero
situation
uh you can see that most clearly in fact
from the
momentum well let's let's concentrate on
the energy both the energy and the
momentum have peculiar things that
happen when the velocity goes to the
speed of
light okay when the velocity goes to the
speed of light the denominator
goes to zero and we don't like
denominators which are equal to
zero
so it's not a good idea to try to study
the limit of massless particles with
these equations but there's another
thing we can do instead of looking at
the relationship between energy and
velocity and mass and velocity get the
velocity out of it all together and just
look at the relationship between moment
um and
energy this is where we're going I want
for future purposes to have the
relationship of the energy to the
momentum for a particle of for a
particle of mass m without having to
worry about what its velocity is all
right so all we have to do let's see
where where are we let's write them down
over here and find the relationship
between them incidentally that
relationship for non-relativistic
physics would just be energy kinetic
energy energy in particular is momentum
squar / twice the
mass we might also throw in mc^ s but uh
this would be this is the analog of
looking for relation between energy and
momentum what does that look like in the
theory of
relativity okay so here we have it we
have energy
equals m / < TK of 1 - V
^2 I'll put the C's back back I I don't
like carrying them around they get
confused m p is equal to
MV over squ < TK of 1us V
^2 okay the square roots in the
denominator are a nuisance so to get rid
of them let's figure out what e^ s is in
terms of p^ s instead of figuring out e
in terms of P let's get e squ in terms
of P squ that'll get rid of the square
roots in the denominator so
e^2 is m m^
2 over 1 - v^ 2 and p^
2 is m^2 v^ 2 over Square < TK of 1 - v^
2 no no square root 1 - v^
2 well I could solve for V what I could
do I could do something complicated I
could solve for v^2 from this equation
and then plug it into here and that
would give me the energy in terms of the
momentum or the momentum in terms of the
energy but it's easier to do than that
all we have to do is take the difference
of these two let's take the difference
of these two e^2 minus
p^2 let's see what we get in the
denominator we're going to get 1 minus V
^2 because both terms have the same
denominator both terms also have
M2 and then this term has 1 and this
term has minus v^
2 so 1us V ^
2 well that's
lucky just e^2 minus p^2 =
m^2 now that's not so surprising e and P
are comp components of a four
Vector the invariant that you make out
of a four Vector is the difference of
the squares of the time components and
the space
components here's what we have we found
the square the difference of the squares
of the time components and the space
components are the square of the mass in
other words the mass is simply the
invariant that you make from the four
Vector of energy and momentum that
that's another way to think about it if
you have a four Vector of energy and
momentum
then the invariant length of that four
Vector is the
mass another way to say it if the
momentum happens to be zero then E and M
are the same thing okay now let's see if
we can figure out where the C's go this
is pure dimensional
analysis
um h
where do you want to put it you want to
put
here numerator or denominator
denominator
numerator c^ s
here I'll tell you how I know in a
minute C squar here and C to the 4th
here now how do I know that first of all
let's forget this
term e s if eal mc^2 e^2 must be m^2 C
4th
that make
sense now energy is typically momentum
times
velocity even in neonian
physics mv^ 2 which is twice sorry mv^ 2
is velocity time
momentum so in
energy this is just unitwise m MV squ
has units of energy velocity time
momentum so energy has units of moment
momentum time
velocity that's the basic connection
between energy and momentum for a
relativistic system for relativistic
particle let's write it
uh just in terms of energy it says that
energy is equal to the square
root of momentum squ * c^
2 plus mass squar time C to the
4th that's a generalization of I was in
certainly Einstein knew it but it's a
generalization of Einstein's eal
mc^2 e = < TK of m^2 C 4th and then if
the object is moving it has momentum you
add p^2 c^2 to it okay so this is our
basic uh energy momentum relation and
notice once we've gone this far we can
now smoothly with no big problem take
the limit that the mass goes to zero and
in that case
energy is just equal to the square root
of p^2
c^2 or just the magnitude of the
momentum time
C you might have
thought that the answer ought to be well
let's see nonrelativistically what's the
answer
nonrelativistically
energy which is 12 mv^
2 is equal to velocity time uh time
sorry is equal to
momentum time velocity over
2 you might have taken this equation and
said okay just plug in velocity equals
the speed of light and you get C * p/2
well you'd be wrong you'd be wrong by a
factor of
two that's the whole effect of
Relativity on the formula for a massless
particle or for a
particle uh moving with a speed of light
is that the energy is twice what you
might have gotten by just using Newton's
equ of course it wouldn't make any sense
to use Newton's
equations uh but PV over2 is the
relation
nonrelativistically PC is the
relationship in
relativity all right I uh I'm not going
to use this now we're going to use it
next time to explore the connection
between waves and
particles and the relationship between
the energy of a wave the momentum of the
wave
uh and the properties of waves and how
those properties of waves are similar to
in fact identical to these relationships
here something noticed partly by
Einstein something or Einstein and the
broley Schrodinger and so
forth that's not because we're getting
into quantum mechanics now we're simply
exploring wave motion and the kinematics
and the Dynamics of moving waves but
there is a strong sense in which a
strong flavor of the relationship
between energy and momentum of particles
on the one hand and frequency and wave
number of waves on the other hand so
that's where we're going next time
[Music]
good the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu